<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Blog-Posts on A minimal Hugo website</title>
    <link>https://example.org/categories/blog-posts/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Blog-Posts on A minimal Hugo website</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 23 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://example.org/categories/blog-posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Week 3</title>
      <link>https://example.org/post/2024/09/23/week-3/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://example.org/post/2024/09/23/week-3/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;So far, we’ve been looking at predictions using data about previous elections, relative to basic&#xD;&#xA;factors (incumbency, party) as well as to measures of economic well-being. However, we have a&#xD;&#xA;much more recent dataset into which we have not yet tapped: the thousands of public opinion&#xD;&#xA;polls that are conducted each year. Through the principles of sampling, polls appear to be&#xD;&#xA;relatively good estimates; a random subset of the population will behave, on average, similarly&#xD;&#xA;to the whole population. But this doesn’t mean polls have always gotten it right in practice; one&#xD;&#xA;of the most significant examples of this was 2016, where by and large, the polls famously&#xD;&#xA;predicted the wrong winner.&#xD;&#xA;This leads us to explore the week’s guiding question: How can we best use polls to predict&#xD;&#xA;election outcomes?&#xD;&#xA;To understand the polls’ behavior so far in the 2024 cycle, I visualized the variation over time&#xD;&#xA;and against key events:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Week 2</title>
      <link>https://example.org/post/2024/09/16/week-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://example.org/post/2024/09/16/week-2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Although last week’s debate drew many viewers and much online discussion, some wondered&#xD;&#xA;how much effect it would really have on the outcome of the 2024 election. After all, some&#xD;&#xA;longstanding theories suggest that a candidate’s campaign strategy, debate performance, and&#xD;&#xA;other actions all fall short to economic variables in the task of prediction. After all, if a voter isn’t&#xD;&#xA;doing well economically, wouldn’t that motivate them to seek out a change? And if they are&#xD;&#xA;doing well, shouldn’t they vote for the incumbent in their own self-interest?&#xD;&#xA;The theory of “pocketbook voting” suggests exactly this: that people vote based on their direct&#xD;&#xA;economic situations. In this theory, the economy is the principal variable in an election, and&#xD;&#xA;should therefore be able to predict the results.&#xD;&#xA;This week, we set out to answer the question: Can we predict election outcomes using only the&#xD;&#xA;state of the economy? If so, how well?&#xD;&#xA;Specifically, I looked at GDP and RDI (real disposable income), the former of which is a&#xD;&#xA;measure of nationwide economic productivity and the latter of which represents how much&#xD;&#xA;direct spending power people have.&#xD;&#xA;Following the idea of pocketbook voting most closely, the variable most tightly correlated with&#xD;&#xA;incumbent votes should be RDI. However, GDP is also often used as a predictive measure&#xD;&#xA;because it indicates the overall state of the economy. I compared both measures in a series of&#xD;&#xA;model fits and visualizations that focused on mapping previous presidential elections to&#xD;&#xA;economic conditions and incumbent vote shares.&#xD;&#xA;I also sometimes omitted the case of 2020: as shown in the below two graphs, the change to&#xD;&#xA;the economy caused by the COVID-19 pandemic was unprecedented and made it a significant&#xD;&#xA;outlier.&#xD;&#xA;The following scatter plots graph these two economic measures against the incumbent party’s&#xD;&#xA;popular vote share.&#xD;&#xA;Including 2020:&#xD;&#xA;&lt;img src=&#34;imgs/B2I1.png&#34; alt=&#34;GDP&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Week 1</title>
      <link>https://example.org/post/2024/09/09/week-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://example.org/post/2024/09/09/week-1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Guiding Questions&lt;/p&gt;&#xD;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This week, we set out to answer two key questions about presidential elections in the United States.&#xD;&#xA;1) How competitive are presidential elections in the United States?&#xD;&#xA;2) Which states vote blue/red and how consistently?&#xD;&#xA;There are many ways to approach these questions, especially with predictive ends in mind. Is it possible to gather enough data points about a state to accurately understand the likelihood of its individual outcome in the upcoming election?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
