<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Home on A minimal Hugo website</title>
    <link>https://example.org/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Home on A minimal Hugo website</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 07 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://example.org/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Week 5</title>
      <link>https://example.org/post/2024/10/07/week-5/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://example.org/post/2024/10/07/week-5/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Week 5: Demographics and Comprehensive Modeling&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This week, we examined the effects of demographic values on voter turnout and vote choice, based on a paper by Kim and Zilinsky (2023).&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The demographics we looked at are age, gender, race, income, and education. Although there are certainly some correlations between demographics and those who vote (active voters are more often older, white, &amp;amp; educated), the study concludes that demographics alone do not tell us that much about partisanship and vote choice. Specifically, a model trained on demographics alone has about a 60% accuracy rate, which holds during our replication of the analysis. This does not significantly improve on a coin flip between the two parties, suggesting that demographics are not a very strong predictor. It was also found that the amount of overall turnout does not push elections in one particular direction.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Week 4</title>
      <link>https://example.org/post/2024/09/30/week-4/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://example.org/post/2024/09/30/week-4/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Incumbency can be an important factor in the results of an election. Incumbents may enjoy such advantages as easy name recognition, ability to take credit for the country&amp;rsquo;s usual steady economic growth, and even the ability to allocate more federal funding to certain states. These advantages seem to lead to 7 out of 11 incumbent presidents winning since 1948. However, much of this advantage extends only to incumbent presidents, not to their parties &amp;ndash; when considering all incumbent parties running for re-election, the statistic falls to 9 out of 19 wins since 1948, which chalks it up to a coin flip.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Welcome</title>
      <link>https://example.org/post/2024/09/27/welcome/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Sep 2024 21:13:14 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://example.org/post/2024/09/27/welcome/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;election-analytics-blog-2024&#34;&gt;Election Analytics Blog 2024&lt;/h1&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Hi! Welcome to my blog. I&amp;rsquo;m Jade and I&amp;rsquo;m part of the Election Analytics course at Harvard, where we are learning how to use data science to build predictive models and analyze the factors that drive elections. Follow along to see my predictions and models for each week leading up to the 2024 election!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Week 3</title>
      <link>https://example.org/post/2024/09/23/week-3/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://example.org/post/2024/09/23/week-3/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;So far, we’ve been looking at predictions using data about previous elections, relative to basic&#xA;factors (incumbency, party) as well as to measures of economic well-being. However, we have a&#xA;much more recent dataset into which we have not yet tapped: the thousands of public opinion&#xA;polls that are conducted each year. Through the principles of sampling, polls appear to be&#xA;relatively good estimates; a random subset of the population will behave, on average, similarly&#xA;to the whole population. But this doesn’t mean polls have always gotten it right in practice; one&#xA;of the most significant examples of this was 2016, where by and large, the polls famously&#xA;predicted the wrong winner.&#xA;This leads us to explore the week’s guiding question: How can we best use polls to predict&#xA;election outcomes?&#xA;To understand the polls’ behavior so far in the 2024 cycle, I visualized the variation over time&#xA;and against key events:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Week 2</title>
      <link>https://example.org/post/2024/09/16/week-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://example.org/post/2024/09/16/week-2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Although last week’s debate drew many viewers and much online discussion, some wondered&#xA;how much effect it would really have on the outcome of the 2024 election. After all, some&#xA;longstanding theories suggest that a candidate’s campaign strategy, debate performance, and&#xA;other actions all fall short to economic variables in the task of prediction. After all, if a voter isn’t&#xA;doing well economically, wouldn’t that motivate them to seek out a change? And if they are&#xA;doing well, shouldn’t they vote for the incumbent in their own self-interest?&#xA;The theory of “pocketbook voting” suggests exactly this: that people vote based on their direct&#xA;economic situations. In this theory, the economy is the principal variable in an election, and&#xA;should therefore be able to predict the results.&#xA;This week, we set out to answer the question: Can we predict election outcomes using only the&#xA;state of the economy? If so, how well?&#xA;Specifically, I looked at GDP and RDI (real disposable income), the former of which is a&#xA;measure of nationwide economic productivity and the latter of which represents how much&#xA;direct spending power people have.&#xA;Following the idea of pocketbook voting most closely, the variable most tightly correlated with&#xA;incumbent votes should be RDI. However, GDP is also often used as a predictive measure&#xA;because it indicates the overall state of the economy. I compared both measures in a series of&#xA;model fits and visualizations that focused on mapping previous presidential elections to&#xA;economic conditions and incumbent vote shares.&#xA;I also sometimes omitted the case of 2020: as shown in the below two graphs, the change to&#xA;the economy caused by the COVID-19 pandemic was unprecedented and made it a significant&#xA;outlier.&#xA;The following scatter plots graph these two economic measures against the incumbent party’s&#xA;popular vote share.&#xA;Including 2020:&#xA;&lt;img src=&#34;imgs/B2I1.png&#34; alt=&#34;GDP&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Week 1</title>
      <link>https://example.org/post/2024/09/09/week-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://example.org/post/2024/09/09/week-1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Guiding Questions&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This week, we set out to answer two key questions about presidential elections in the United States.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;How competitive are presidential elections in the United States?&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Which states vote blue/red and how consistently?&#xA;There are many ways to approach these questions, especially with predictive ends in mind. Is it possible to gather enough data points about a state to accurately understand the likelihood of its individual outcome in the upcoming election?&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Analysis &amp;amp; Visualization&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Another Note on A blogdown Tutorial</title>
      <link>https://example.org/note/2017/06/14/another-note/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://example.org/note/2017/06/14/another-note/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I just discovered &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.apreshill.com/blog/2020-12-new-year-new-blogdown/&#34;&gt;an awesome tutorial&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;strong&gt;blogdown&lt;/strong&gt; written by Alison. I have to admit this is &lt;em&gt;the&lt;/em&gt; best &lt;strong&gt;blogdown&lt;/strong&gt; tutorial I have seen so far.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://www.apreshill.com/blog/2020-12-new-year-new-blogdown/03-blogdown-2021.png&#34; alt=&#34;Alison&amp;rsquo;s blogdown tutorial&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Quick Note on Two Beautiful Websites</title>
      <link>https://example.org/note/2017/06/13/a-quick-note/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://example.org/note/2017/06/13/a-quick-note/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;To me, the two most impressive websites based on &lt;strong&gt;blogdown&lt;/strong&gt; are:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://robjhyndman.com&#34;&gt;Rob J Hyndman&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo;s personal website.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://livefreeordichotomize.com&#34;&gt;Live Free or Dichotomize&lt;/a&gt; by Lucy and Nick &lt;em&gt;et al&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m sure there will be more.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>About</title>
      <link>https://example.org/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://example.org/about/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I am developing a predictive model for the 2024 election. Check out the blog posts (a new one will drop each Monday)!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
