<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Week2 on A minimal Hugo website</title>
    <link>https://example.org/tags/week2/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Week2 on A minimal Hugo website</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 16 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://example.org/tags/week2/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Week 2</title>
      <link>https://example.org/post/2024/09/16/week-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://example.org/post/2024/09/16/week-2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Although last week’s debate drew many viewers and much online discussion, some wondered&#xA;how much effect it would really have on the outcome of the 2024 election. After all, some&#xA;longstanding theories suggest that a candidate’s campaign strategy, debate performance, and&#xA;other actions all fall short to economic variables in the task of prediction. After all, if a voter isn’t&#xA;doing well economically, wouldn’t that motivate them to seek out a change? And if they are&#xA;doing well, shouldn’t they vote for the incumbent in their own self-interest?&#xA;The theory of “pocketbook voting” suggests exactly this: that people vote based on their direct&#xA;economic situations. In this theory, the economy is the principal variable in an election, and&#xA;should therefore be able to predict the results.&#xA;This week, we set out to answer the question: Can we predict election outcomes using only the&#xA;state of the economy? If so, how well?&#xA;Specifically, I looked at GDP and RDI (real disposable income), the former of which is a&#xA;measure of nationwide economic productivity and the latter of which represents how much&#xA;direct spending power people have.&#xA;Following the idea of pocketbook voting most closely, the variable most tightly correlated with&#xA;incumbent votes should be RDI. However, GDP is also often used as a predictive measure&#xA;because it indicates the overall state of the economy. I compared both measures in a series of&#xA;model fits and visualizations that focused on mapping previous presidential elections to&#xA;economic conditions and incumbent vote shares.&#xA;I also sometimes omitted the case of 2020: as shown in the below two graphs, the change to&#xA;the economy caused by the COVID-19 pandemic was unprecedented and made it a significant&#xA;outlier.&#xA;The following scatter plots graph these two economic measures against the incumbent party’s&#xA;popular vote share.&#xA;Including 2020:&#xA;Excluding 2020:&#xA;Using linear regressions, I created lines of best fit as follows for the 2020-excluded datasets:&#xA;Although they both appear positively correlated, the statistics ended up having different&#xA;significance values. Focusing only on the 2020-excluded values, here are some of the statistics&#xA;for GDP and RDI (all when compared to popular vote share):&#xA;Slope&#xA;Coefficient&#xA;Correlation R squared P value&#xA;GDP 0.7366 0.569918 0.3248066 0.0135&#xA;(significant!)&#xA;RDI 0.4604 0.3338966 0.1114869 0.176 (not!)&#xA;Based on these numbers, it’s clear that GDP is a more significant or substantive predictor of&#xA;popular vote election results. However, I wondered if using both variables together could be an&#xA;even better predictor.&#xA;As a result, I also created a combined multivariate linear regression between these two&#xA;variables, which had interesting results.&#xA;Coefficients:&#xA;Estimate Std. Error t value Pr(&amp;gt;|t|)&#xA;(Intercept) 49.40880 1.75347 28.178 2.1e-14 ***&#xA;RDPI_growth_quarterly -0.01269 0.36442 -0.035 0.9727&#xA;GDP_growth_quarterly 0.74367 0.34155 2.177 0.0458 *&#xA;When controlling for GDP, the coefficient for RDI was actually negative!&#xA;I also plotted in-sample error for each of the three models (GDP, RDI, Both), in both line charts&#xA;and histograms, as shown:&#xA;The histograms suggest that using GDP alone appears to create the most accurate predictions,&#xA;so the final prediction for 2024 will also be based on that model:&#xA;The model predicts that the incumbent party (the Democrats) will receive 51.58486% of the&#xA;popular vote in the 2024 presidential election.&#xA;Overall, although there is a somewhat significant correlation between GDP and election results,&#xA;using economic situations alone does not create a perfect model; there are various outliers,&#xA;especially the year 2020. There are many other reasons that 2024 could be an outlier (Biden&#xA;stepping down and Harris stepping in last-minute; the outlier-filled candidacy of Trump; the road&#xA;to economic recovery from COVID) and thus the usual economic models may not work as well&#xA;for it as they have for past elections.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
