<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Week2 on A minimal Hugo website</title>
    <link>https://example.org/tags/week2/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Week2 on A minimal Hugo website</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 16 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://example.org/tags/week2/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Week 2</title>
      <link>https://example.org/post/2024/09/16/week-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://example.org/post/2024/09/16/week-2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Although last week’s debate drew many viewers and much online discussion, some wondered&#xA;how much effect it would really have on the outcome of the 2024 election. After all, some&#xA;longstanding theories suggest that a candidate’s campaign strategy, debate performance, and&#xA;other actions all fall short to economic variables in the task of prediction. After all, if a voter isn’t&#xA;doing well economically, wouldn’t that motivate them to seek out a change? And if they are&#xA;doing well, shouldn’t they vote for the incumbent in their own self-interest?&#xA;The theory of “pocketbook voting” suggests exactly this: that people vote based on their direct&#xA;economic situations. In this theory, the economy is the principal variable in an election, and&#xA;should therefore be able to predict the results.&#xA;This week, we set out to answer the question: Can we predict election outcomes using only the&#xA;state of the economy? If so, how well?&#xA;Specifically, I looked at GDP and RDI (real disposable income), the former of which is a&#xA;measure of nationwide economic productivity and the latter of which represents how much&#xA;direct spending power people have.&#xA;Following the idea of pocketbook voting most closely, the variable most tightly correlated with&#xA;incumbent votes should be RDI. However, GDP is also often used as a predictive measure&#xA;because it indicates the overall state of the economy. I compared both measures in a series of&#xA;model fits and visualizations that focused on mapping previous presidential elections to&#xA;economic conditions and incumbent vote shares.&#xA;I also sometimes omitted the case of 2020: as shown in the below two graphs, the change to&#xA;the economy caused by the COVID-19 pandemic was unprecedented and made it a significant&#xA;outlier.&#xA;The following scatter plots graph these two economic measures against the incumbent party’s&#xA;popular vote share.&#xA;Including 2020:&#xA;&lt;img src=&#34;%22imgs%5CB2I1.png%22&#34; alt=&#34;GDP&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
